Okay, so in this one, we are going to be listening for our keystrokes.
To do this, we're going to add an event listener to our document,
listening to the keydown event.
We're going to be listening for if we are backspacing or if we're entering a character.
We're going to need to add some variables to track what has been typed,
what index we are at in our characters.
We'll need to actually split our long text string into an array of single characters so that we can track that.
We're also going to track errors and then eventually we'll also need to create a way to actually scroll our text once we get far enough in that we need to do that.
So that we can actually see the remaining text and continue typing.
Okay, so let's dive right in.
So I'm going to go ahead and actually move the stuff up here to the top,
just to put all of my variables in one place and my constants.
Okay, so the first thing we need, we're going to need a let total typed and this is going to be a string
and we are also going to need let current char times our character index equals zero.
So again, we're going to split this long text into an array and we are concerned with where we are in that array.
And we'll also want to track our errors, let errors equal zero for now,
but this is going to eventually impact our words per minute.
Okay, and from here what we're going to do, let's just make sure everything is still good.
Okay, yep, everything is still good.
We are going to comment out a title here for handle typing over the displayed text and scrolling.
So you'll notice that I didn't have a separate input and then a box with just a bunch of text.
I wanted to actually be able to type within the text container that's showing the text and just highlight the text.
I just think that that looks a lot better and so that's why we're doing it this way.
Okay, so document, add event listener, bracket, single quotes,
key downs or listening to this key down event. So every time we press a key on our keyboard,
this event is going to be triggered and we'll do bracket E for our event and then our arrow function,
curly brackets, press enter, semicolon there and we're going to start with our backspace.
So we're going to track if we're backspacing, we are going back in our character index.
So we do need to track when we have a backspace key hit.
So if E dot key equals three equal signs, so it exactly equals backspace,
then if our total typed dot length is more than zero,
so keep in mind if we are at the very beginning and we hit backspace,
we don't really want anything to happen.
And that's why we have this condition here, but if we're not at the very beginning,
we want to actually lower our current character index.
So current care index equals math dot max bracket current care index minus one or zero.
So let's say that we're 10 characters in, we want to be able to go back one.
So to nine or we want to go to zero, so whichever one is bigger.
So for at 10, we're going to minus one and go to nine.
If we're at the very beginning, it'll just be zero.
So it'll just stay at the first position.
And total typed is going to be equal to total typed dot slice zero minus one.
So this is going to remove one character, so this is a long string of what we've typed.
It's going to remove one character off of it.
That is what our slice is doing here.
So if we are not backspacing, else bracket, sorry, else if our E dot key,
dot key, dot link is equal to one.
So we only want to track single keys that are being entered.
We don't want to track combinations of keys at once.
And we also don't want to track if we're pressing our control key or our meta keys.
We just want to track basically letters in this case.
Okay.
And in this case, our total typed is going to add.
So plus equals is to add the value of that keystroke.
So if I typed j, it would add j to the total typed string that we have.
Now go ahead and just minimize these for now.
So we just kind of see our values there a little bit.
And then we're going to increment our current character index.
Okay.
So what we're going to do here is I'm going to add a few console logs so that we can better understand what's happening here.
So we'll do E dot key.
And we're going to log that.
And then we're also going to log our total, total typed, total typed.
And we're also going to log our current, our index, our current index.
Okay.
So let's actually see what is happening here.
So I'm going to type the letter j.
Okay.
So we can see we have our event key is j.
Our total typed is j and our current character index is one.
So if I just type a bunch of other random letters, you can see that it's taking in one letter at a time.
And it's adding them to our string here.
And it is incrementing our index.
So you can see it just keeps going up.
And then if I were to hit backspace, you can see that the key is backspace.
And the total typed, we actually removed the letter h at the end and our current index went down as well.
So this is what is going to help us track where we are and what the total of what we've typed is.
It's going to be one long string.
Of course, it's going to have spaces in it as well.
But I'm just showing you how the mechanism is going to work for tracking our backspace and our regular letters that we are entering.
Okay, so let's move on from here.
So I guess I'll leave that console log for now, but I'll remove it in a bit.
Now from here, we want to create a constant for our text array.
And this is going to be our long text that we generated up here.
So it put our long array into one long string.
And then we're going to go ahead and actually split it.
And we're going to split every single character, even spaces.
So it'll be one character per entry in our text array.
So let's go ahead and, well, I guess we can console log.
We'll join, I guess, I can't do it there because it's not going to show up.
Let's do a separate console log.
That wouldn't work because we haven't initiated text array yet.
So you can't console log up here.
But let's go ahead and try this now.
So I can see I have to actually press a button.
But now you can see we have a 1300 and 98 long array.
And if I expand it, you can see that we have each single character including spaces in an array.
And basically what we're doing with our total typed is we're going to match character for character.
So if the first character is F and the first character here is N, I know that that's incorrect.
We're doing a character for character comparison.
And then we're going through our index in order to tell, okay, second character, did I type A?
And then if it's A here, then that's correct.
And then we can add our correct class or we can add our error class and increment our errors, etc.
So that is how that's going to work.
We're basically splitting total typed into checking character by character.
And we're splitting our big string into a bunch of character items in an array.
Okay, the next thing we're going to do is we're actually going to reset our text container.
Intertext is going to be nothing.
So we're going to reset it.
And we're also going to reset our errors to be zero.
The reason we have to put this in here as well is in case we actually are running the test once and then hitting the try again.
So we're not actually reloading the page in that case.
Even though we're setting it as zero there, we'll need to set it again.
So I added it there.
And then now we're going to need to loop through.
So four, let i equals zero.
So we're going to start at the index of zero.
And our i is going to go until we get to the length of our text array,
which it's probably never going to reach because it's almost 1400 characters.
And I'm going to keep incrementing as long as we don't hit the limit, which again, I don't think we will.
And from here, we're going to create a span.
And this is going to be equal to document create element and single quotes spans.
We're going to create a span. And if i is less than our total typed length.
And keep in mind, we're starting at zero here, but our total typed length is starting at one in this case.
So if you remember, if I press this, that length is one, it's not starting at zero.
And you'll see we already reset everything here.
Okay, so if i is less than our total type length, if our total typed,
and we're going to use that index, is equal to our text array index.
So they're both zero indexed. Then that span, we're going to add a class list.
Single quotes of correct. So we're going to add that green styling.
Else, span, class list, add error. And we're also going to increment our errors.
Okay, and then for our span, we're actually going to add that text content.
And we're going to add it.
We're going to add that single character of that index from the text array.
And that's going to be the text content for the span we've created.
And we're going to add the class of correct or error. And it's going to make it red or green.
And then we're going to append the child to our text container.
And we're going to append that span.
Okay, so let's go ahead and check that out.
Okay, so we're going to go actually over to our elements here.
So you see we have everything loaded. And if I type something, you can see that.
Okay, if we open up our text container here, you see that we have a bunch of spans.
And they are the individual characters. And you see I typed E correctly.
And it has the class of correct. And you see that it's green.
And if I type the next character is F and it's D, I have error.
And then if I just keep going, see that I have a bunch of errors.
Which it's doing what it's supposed to do.
And you can see that we have our character index is moving up.
This is our total type length. And you see all of our keys that we're entering here.
You might have noticed something unusual though in our text container.
We have lost all of our spaces.
So we are going to need to fix that.
But this video is getting a little bit long.
So let's take a break here.
And we'll finish up dealing with our spaces and our scrolling to the left in the next video.
video. I'll see you then, bye for now.